Top of today's daf is ל"א, Lamed Aleph, 31. And we pick
up at the bottom or the middle of ל"א עמוד ב Lamed
Amud Bet at the two dots. And we are and we're dealing
with this issue about this institution of lending money to the כהן,
Kohen, לוי, Levi, or the עני, Ani, and sort of an arrangement
that you'll give them תרומות Terumot and מעשרות Ma'asrot to pay back
for the money that you just lent them, and sort of and
then you handle that yourself.
But within that context we have here a similar discussion. So let's
take a look. תנו רבנן. Tanoo Rabbanan. ישראל Yisrael she'amar l'Levi, 'מעשר
יש לך בידי,' Ma'aser yesh lacha b'yadi, ישראל Yisrael said to a
לוי, Levi, 'You have מעשר Ma'aser in my possession,' אין חוששין לתרומת
מעשר שבו. ein chosheshin l'trumat ma'aser shebo. You don't have to worry
about that. Now the הלכה halakha is you don't have to worry
about that there might be תרומת מעשר trumat ma'aser in the מעשר.
ma'aser. Right? תרומת מעשר Trumat ma'aser is the tenth of the tenth
that the לוי Levi separates and gives to the כהן. Kohen. Okay?
But if he said to him, 'כור מעשר יש לך בידי,' Kore
ma'aser yesh lacha b'yadi, you have a specific measure of מעשר. ma'aser.
If he didn't just say 'you've got a pile of מעשר ma'aser
in my house,' you have a כור, kore, you have a whatever.
I don't even know what volume measurements are for wheat, but anyway,
a bushel, a peck, whatever it is. 30 סאה. se'ah. Oh, good,
now we know. 30 סאה se'ah of...
anyway, you have a certain measure of מעשר ma'aser in my possession,
חוששין לתרומת מעשר שבו, chosheshin l'trumat ma'aser shebo, you're concerned about the
תרומת מעשר. trumat ma'aser. So what the heck does any of this
mean? Which is what the גמרא Gemara says.
The גמרא Gemara says, 'מאי
קאמר?' Mai ka'amar? What is this saying? Like, I can't even parse
this. So אמר אביי, amar Abaye, so says אביי, Abaye, הכי
קאמר, hachi ka'amar, this is what it's saying. ישראל Yisrael she'amar l'Levi,
thank you so much, ישראל Yisrael she'amar l'Levi, 'מעשר יש לך בידי,
Ma'aser yesh lacha b'yadi, והילך דמיו.' v'heilach damav. Says, 'Look,' and this
very much fits in the context of our משנה, Mishnah, 'I separated
off some מעשר ma'aser in my home. Okay? I'll give it to
you, you know, but you know, I mean it's yours. I separated
it off, I had you in mind, whatever it is, it's yours.
Okay? Let me buy it back off of you. All right? So
take this money instead, let me buy it back off of you,
and I'll just keep the grain in my house.' All right? So
that very much sort of fits the context of the משנה. Mishnah.
So והילך דמיו, v'heilach damav, here's the money. אין חוששין שמא עשאו
תרומת מעשר על מקום אחר. Ein chosheshin shema asa'o trumat ma'aser al
makom acher. You're not concerned that the לוי, Levi, before he... this
is the way תוספות Tosafot explains it... before he took the money,
because as soon as he takes the money the sale was binding,
why? Because even though מטלטלין, metaltelin, cattle, whatever, are not... money doesn't
make the transaction, it's taking possession of it. But as soon as
he takes the money, I've taken possession of it, because it's all
it's in my house. Right? So if so, תוספות Tosafot says, but
the concern is he says, 'Will you sell me that מעשר? ma'aser?
I separated מעשר ma'aser yesterday. It's yours. Let me now buy it
back off of you.' Okay? By the way, you realize again how
this is like, I mean, a good way of me saving some
money. Like, you have a thousand dollars worth of מעשר, ma'aser, I
find a לוי Levi who otherwise wasn't expecting to get the מעשר
ma'aser from me, and I could say to him, 'That'll be your
מעשר ma'aser if I could buy it off of you for two
hundred dollars,' or something like that. So anyway, I'm not saying that
that's what the case is saying, but you know, one wonders about
how some of these things might have played out in real life.
So anyway, before... so if you say yes, you agree to the
sale, then when we're not concerned that before you take the money
and the sale is binding, of me selling it back to you,
or you selling it back to me, right? So now I'm saying
it's yours. So now before it's binding, before the sale back to
me takes effect, maybe he'll say, 'Ah, and what I'm going to
do is I'm going to make all that מעשר ma'aser תרומת מעשר
trumat ma'aser on other מעשר ma'aser I have in my house.' Okay?
Because here's the לוי, Levi, right? He's got a thousand bushels or
whatever of מעשר ma'aser in his house, and now you've just given
him a hundred bushels of מעשר. ma'aser. So he'll say, 'Great! I'll
turn that hundred bushels of מעשר ma'aser into the מעשר ma'aser off
of the thousand I've got in my house,' whatever. And now what
happens? I just bought it off of you, but now I'm left
with תרומה trumah in my house.
Right? How do you make it the second just by saying it?
Yeah,
verbal. Right? הרי זו תרומת מעשר. Harei zu trumat ma'aser. Might even
be able to think it, we'll see in a minute. Okay? So
you understand the problem. I thought I was buying from him this
grain that I could eat. I would have to take מעשר ma'aser
from it, תרומת מעשר trumat ma'aser I mean, תרומת מעשר trumat ma'aser
from it, but at least 90 percent I could eat. Do we
have to be concerned that before the sale went through, he went
ahead and he used, turned it all into תרומת מעשר trumat ma'aser
based on other מעשר ma'aser that he had and now I can't
eat any of it? Now it's effectively all תרומה.
trumah. Turned it into תרומת מעשר trumat ma'aser like that and the
לוי Levi then takes the 200 dollars, is that גניבה? geneva?
Well, that's essentially what the גמרא's Gemara going to say. Okay, so
the גמרא's Gemara going to say, yeah,
who does the separate...
who are... who's acting of תרומת מעשר? trumat ma'aser?
Okay, Michael here is our official לוי. Levi. Okay? I'm going ahead
and I'm separating off the מעשר ma'aser from my grain. Here it
is. Then I go to Michael and I say, 'Michael, that מעשר
ma'aser in my house, that's yours.' Maybe
דזכין, d'zachin, maybe we have a third party to קונה koneh it
for him, okay? But I'm going to... right? And then I'm going
to say, 'What? Well, I have to make it yours so now
I can buy it back off of you.'
But he doesn't take it.
Right? I like I said, maybe we maybe we do a קנין
חליפין, kinyan chalifin, we do something that now it's his. So someone
else is קונה koneh it for him. Exactly! And now I say,
'Sell it back to me.' So in the process right before he
sells it back to me, we're not concerned he turned that all
into תרומת מעשר trumat ma'aser and now I'm just stuck with a
lot of
תרומה. trumah. It was 100 bushels of מעשר. maaser. So in that
case והילך דמי חוששין שמא עשאו תרומה ומעשר על מקום אחר. v'heilech
d'mei chosheshin shema asa'o truma u'maaser al makom acher. So the reason
we didn't suspect Michael before wasn't because we thought he was so
honest, was because he didn't know how much it was. Now you
know, but you can't, like if you know, was it a tiny
amount, was it a large amount? You had no idea how much
it was so you can't use it for תרומת מעשר trumat maaser
if you don't know the amount we're talking about.
I can't say like
you know, oh yeah, however much it is I'll figure it out
later, maybe. But anyway, but if it's a very specific amount, so
then he says great, it's 100 bushels, I'll make it תרומת מעשר
trumat maaser on the other 900 bushels that I've got. Okay, so
if he knows the exact amount we are afraid that he did
this switcheroo on me before I was able to buy it back.
So the Gemara says, okay, that reads very nicely in the בריתא,
Baraita, but the Gemara says אטו ברשיעי עסקינן? atu b'rishi'ei askinan? Are
we talking about wicked people? דשקלו דמי ומחלי להו תרומת מעשר? deshaklu
d'mei u'machlei lehu trumat maaser? They take money for it and then
they've turned it into תרומת מעשר? trumat maaser? Right, so like if
you know I'd known that I wouldn't have bought it then, the
whole sale anyway should be void, it should be a מקח טעות.
mekach ta'ut. Right? So the Gemara says that can't be פשט. pshat.
Can't be פשט pshat that we really are חושש choshesh that Michael
did such a thing, and if he did such a thing, I
can't even imagine that the sale would be good because then I
bought it בטעות. b'ta'ut. I thought it was מעשר maaser and he
turned it into תרומת מעשר trumat maaser before I could buy it.
You wanted to say something? No?
Is תרומת מעשר trumat maaser not a fixed amount?
It is a fixed amount. It is a tenth of the מעשר.
maaser.
So, so what was it that he turned the whole thing into?
Yes, this was 100 bushels, he's got 900 other bushels of מעשר
maaser in his house, that's על מקום אחר. al makom acher. Okay?
Alright, so that was a nice read of the בריתא, Baraita, but
it would, I mean in terms of you know the language of
the בריתא Baraita it fits, but but it's why it would be
crazy to think that that would be that we would be concerned
that he would do such a thing. So the Gemara says like
this, אלא, ela, here's try number two, אמר רב משרשיא בריה דרב
אידי הכי קאמר, amar Rav Mesharshiya brei de-Rav Idi hachi ka'amar, here's
what it's saying. ישראל שאמר לבן לוי, Yisrael she'amar l'ven Levi, so
here I am, I'm going to go to that Michael again, my
official לוי Levi for today, and I say to him the following:
מעשר לאביך בידי, maaser l'avicha beyadi, your father left over some מעשר
maaser in my possession. So no longer was I מפריש מעשר mafrish
maaser and I'm giving it to you, your father entrusted some מעשר
maaser to me, okay, before he passed away. We won't make Michael
sorry. No עין הרע. ayin hara. Okay, I say it to לוי.
Levi. Okay, before he passed away. מעשר לאביך בידי. maaser l'avicha beyadi.
I'm losing my place. והילך דמי, v'heilech d'mei,
here's the money, אין חוששין שמא עשאו אביו תרומת מעשר על מקום
אחר. ein chosheshin shema asa'o aviv trumat maaser al makom acher. So
really it's not a question of right now what's happening, it's really
a question, forget the לוי Levi that I'm selling it to right
now. What I want to know is some לוי Levi entrusted מעשר
maaser into my possession and then passed away. Okay, that's basically the
case. Some לוי Levi entrusted מעשר maaser and then he passed up,
passed away. Do I have to be concerned that that became
תרומת מעשר trumat maaser before he died? Now the question is why
why is it my issue? It's not my מעשר. maaser. So the
issue is I'm trying to buy the מעשר maaser back off now
from the son. So it is my issue. Entrusted מעשר maaser to
me, I'm going to buy it now back from the son or
I want to, but do I have to be concerned that the
father before he died, and he's not a רשע, rasha, he wasn't
planning on selling it to me, before he died maybe he made
it into תרומת
מעשר.
trumat
maaser.
Okay the scenario of somebody as a third party, yeah, the question
is if somebody has מעשר maaser and he died, do we assume,
oh you mean like do his sons assume that it was? That's
an interesting question. Like maybe the dynamics might be different if it's
entrusted to another person, but you're right. I mean in general that's
the question that the ראשונים Rishonim ask, which is like you know
when a חבר שמת, chaver shemeit, the Gemara has a lot of
actually cases about this, that when somebody dies you assume that all
the grain that he left over is all מתוקנים metukanim and you
don't have problems with it. Yeah, I mean תוספות Tosafot really doesn't
understand how this fits into other sort of scenarios.
It wouldn't be easy על מקום אחר al makom acher because if
if the מעשר maaser we're talking about contains within it תרומת מעשר,
trumat maaser, but you don't know the north side or the south
side, sometimes,
no no no, because no but but if he didn't, right, there
are three scenarios. He did nothing to it and it's all מעשר
maaser waiting for תרומת מעשר trumat maaser to be taken. So now
number two is he took תרומת מעשר trumat maaser and we don't
know where it is, okay. The Gemara I guess feels that that's
the least likely scenario because to assume that this is all that
there's a differentiation of what happened. And the third scenario is it's
all תרומת מעשר trumat maaser based on some other grain somewhere else.
Alright, and anyway that's the worst case scenario but you're okay. So
anyway it says, so anyway so there's this grain and I want
to know whether I have to be concerned about what happened before
this guy died. Okay. והילך דמי, v'heilech d'mei, and I'm trying to
now buy this grain, אין חוששין שמא עשאו אביו תרומת מעשר על
מקום אחר. ein chosheshin shema asa'o aviv trumat maaser al makom acher.
I don't have to be concerned that the father, you know, turned
this into תרומת מעשר. trumat maaser. כור מעשר לאביך בידי, kor maaser
l'avicha beyadi,
if I ever say it was a כור מעשר, kor maaser, and
presumably
the reason I'm articulating it that way is because that's how it
was entrusted to me. Meaning that's the assumption. If I say your
father entrusted some מעשר, maaser, the presumption is he didn't say I'm
giving you 100 bushels of מעשר. maaser. He just says here's some
מעשר maaser let me keep it by you. But if he said
I'm giving... giving you a hundred bushels of מעשר, maaser, then it
was known to him and the amount was clear and articulated. So
if that's now how it was entrusted to me and what I'm
reporting, now I have to be concerned oh so the father was
aware of exactly how much maybe he did make it into תרומת
מעשר. trumas maaser. Okay, in that case הלכתא דמא ואי בעית חושש
שמא עשאו אביו תרומת מעשר ממקום אחר. halchata demai ve'ee bayis choshesh
shema asao aviv trumas maaser mimakom acher.
So basically what it boils down to is somebody a לוי Levi
dies and leaves behind מעשר maaser and he articulated how much it
was and he gave it maybe it's דווקא davka he gave it
to someone else, but anyway do we have to be concerned that
at some stage it became תרומת מעשר trumas maaser the whole amount?
So the גמרא Gemara says
so תוספות Tosfos asks the questions that some of you were asking
like it's a general issue and anyway don't we always assume that
when somebody dies he's left all of his stuff in a fixed
state? But the גמרא Gemara asks a slightly different question: וכי נחשדו
חברים לתרום שלא מן המוקף? v'chi nechsh'du chaveirim litrom shelo min hamukaf?
I don't get it. If all of this should be תרומת מעשר
trumas maaser on some other grain somewhere else, so they're not all
in the same space. מוקף Mukaf is sort of like it's all
sort of like contained, surrounded. Okay, the idea of separating you know
תרומה, truma, separating מעשר maaser is that it's something taken from a
whole, which means all the stuff is together and you're and you're
you know a certain part is being separated from the rest. So
technically it works. I could have grain in this room and I
could have other grain you know three states over and I could
say this grain is תרומה truma on the stuff I've got like
in Atlanta, right? Or this grain is תרומת מעשר trumas maiser on
the מעשר maiser I have in Hawaii. Okay back to Hawaii. Anyway
so that works, it does work because I can verbally designate it,
but it's not the it's not the way it's supposed to be
done. It's supposed to all physically be together. And that's called you
know מן המוקף min hamukaf or שלא מן המוקף, shelo min hamukaf,
if it's all contained in the same space when I'm separating it
out. So to be concerned that this guy died and turned this
מעשר maaser into תרומת מעשר, trumas maaser, the entire amount, on מעשר
maaser that exists somewhere else, I'm basically suspecting him of violating you
know the normal לכתחילה, l'chatchila, the normal way. What yes so that's
funny we're always assuming we're dealing with חברים, chaveirim, I guess if
he's not a חבר chaveir maybe I have to be concerned I
don't know. The only other option and then it becomes a דמאי
Demai question and then right okay right.
Anyway according to לוי Levi believe? What? I'm on the גמרא Gemara
today.
Yeah and you said you did it?
No no no it says like you know what he told me
that that he you know he said it was מעשר maaser but
you know he really said it's תרומת מעשר. trumas maaser.
Yeah I don't know, I'm not going to... yeah I mean to
some degree I mean it's like an interesting question to like a
דיני ממונות deini mamonus element but there's also like a you know
about עד אחד נאמן באיסורין ed echad ne'eman b'issurin so like I...
which one sort of would dominate in that case would be an
interesting question. You know what I mean? Do we see him as
testifying? Anyway but okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: וכי
נחשדו חברים לתרום שלא מן המוקף? v'chi nechsh'du chaveirim litrom shelo min
hamukaf? I don't get it. Why should we suspect that this guy
who presumably was a חבר chaveir and somebody scrupulous about the laws
of תרומות ומעשרות trumos u'maasros would have turned this amount into תרומת
מעשר trumas maaser on some other grain? You're not supposed to do
it if it's not in the same space. So the גמרא Gemara
says אלא אמר רב אשי הכא קאמר. ella amar Rav Ashi hacha
ka'amar. Let's try number three. בן ישראל שמע ללוי, Ben Yisrael shama
l'Levi, בן ישראל Ben Yisrael says to the לוי, Levi, כך אמר
לי אבא, kach amar li Abba, here's what your... so now he's
saying to... now he's not reporting to what that the the guy
who the guy who gave me the grain died. Okay that was
the scenario number two. No, it's that the guy is saying my
father died and here's what my father said. שמע ללוי כך אמר
לי אבא, shama l'Levi kach amar li Abba, this is what my
father said, מעשר לך בידי, maaser l'cha b'yadi,
oh מעשר לאביך בידי. maaser l'avicha b'yadi. My father before he died
told me that you know I he had some מעשר maaser that
belonged to you. He separated off מעשר maaser from his grain. ראובן
Reuven is saying my dad יעקב Yaakov before he died separated off
מעשר maaser from his grain and he said that it should be
for you. Or for your or for your father. לוי's Levi father
has just thrown in, let's not even worry about that, okay? It
should be for you. Okay so now I want to know whether
what my dad might have done to that grain is what ראובן
Reuven is saying. Okay? So ומשמע דחוששין לתרומת מעשר שבו. u'mashma d'chosh'shon
l'trumas maaser she'bo. Now ומשמע דחוששין לתרומת מעשר שבו. u'mashma d'chosh'shon l'trumas
maaser she'bo. כיון דלא קייץ לא הוי מתני
ליה בעל הבית. keivan d'lo kayitz lo havu masnelei ba'al habayis. So
the question here is did
my father, can we assume do you a favor? He said I
want to make sure that you know that our friend לוי Levi
there you know gets this מעשר maaser that I've separated off for
him. And then and then the father died. So now here's the
question: is it all מעשר maaser or is there still תרומת מעשר
trumas maaser that hasn't been separated? Right? Raw מעשר maaser has תרומת
מעשר trumas maaser that hasn't been separated. But maybe the father was
being so nice that he actually did the job of separating off
the תרומת מעשר trumas maaser and all of this is like you
know clean מעשר maaser that can go to the לוי. Levi. So
that's the question. Do you have to be concerned, or not concerned
as a bad thing, you know can you can you hope that
the father took off the תרומת מעשר? trumas maaser? So let's read
that again. So he
said כך אמר לי אבא מעשר לך בידי ומעשר לאביך בידי, kach
amar li Abba maaser l'cha b'yadi u'maaser l'avicha b'yadi, חוששין chosh'shon you're
concerned
לתרומת מעשר שבו, l'trumas maaser she'bo, that there still is תרומת מעשר
trumas maaser in that מעשר maaser and it's raw מעשר maaser call
it and it still has to separate תרומת מעשר. trumas maaser. כיון
דלא קייץ, keivan d'lo kayitz, since the amount was not articulated or
and maybe therefore the father didn't even know the exact amount, לא
הוה מתקן ליה בעל הבית. lo hava metaken leih baal habayis. He
wouldn't have separated off the תרומת מעשר. trumas maaser. If, however, he
said כור מעשר לך בידי kor maaser lach beyadei or כור מעשר
לאביך בידי, kor maaser l'avicha beyadei, if the father said before he
died, you know, there's 100 bushels of מעשר maaser for that לוי,
Levi, you know, that's going that I've separated to that לוי, Levi,
in that case, since he articulated the amount and he knew the
amount, אין חוששין לתרומת מעשר שבו. ein chosheshin l'trumas maaser shebo. We
don't have to be concerned that he, that
it's raw. He can assume that if he left it over for
the לוי, Levi, he made it, you know, clean, he took out...
that's the phrase I'm using, he just took off the תרומת מעשר
trumas maaser so it was all מעשר maaser that goes to the
לוי. Levi. He did that for the לוי, Levi, before he died.
Okay, כיון דקץ, keivan d'katz, since the amount is קייץ, kayitz, it's
precise and it's
known, so תיקוני תקניה בעל הבית, tikkunei takniya baal habayis, he fixed
it up for the לוי Levi so the לוי Levi could get
pure clean מעשר maaser with תרומת מעשר trumas maaser already fully taken
from it.
That's what it seems to say.
Right, right. If you buy sometimes a box of מצות, matzos, right,
and it says on it חלה גנומן, challah genummen,
right, which means the חלה challah was taken. So here you give
the מעשר maaser to the לוי Levi and it has תרומת מעשר
גנומן. trumas maaser genummen. Okay, so he can eat it, it's already
been fixed up. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says: דאדרבה. d'adarabba. Yeah,
exactly. So גמרא... Gemara... okay, so now we're satisfied. Okay, that works.
It probably doesn't at all fit the original language of the ברייתא,
Beraisa, but at least it's a scenario that makes sense. Okay, so
now the assumption is somebody before he dies leaves over מעשר maaser
the same way we say that normally a חבר chaver doesn't die
with leaving his grain unfixed, so if he leaves over מעשר maaser
to be given to a particular לוי, Levi, maybe before he's decided
who it's given to it's a different story, we can assume he
fixed it up perfect for the לוי Levi and already took out
the תרומת מעשר. trumas maaser. If he articulated the amount, if the
amount was known and articulated, then we can assume he fixed it
up.
Yes, so it actually goes the opposite
of the original text of the ברייתא. Beraisa. Yeah, let's not... yes,
if you go back and look at the original language of the
ברייתא, Beraisa, it flipped it around. Okay, moving on though. But at
least we got a scenario that works. So the גמרא Gemara says
like
this: וכי יש לו רשות לבעל הבית לתרום תרומת מעשר? v'chi yesh
lo reshus l'baal habayis litrom trumas maaser? Now we are able to
finally turn to an interesting הלכתי halachic question. Wait a minute! Since
when does the בעל הבית baal habayis get to take תרומת מעשר
trumas maaser from the מעשר? maaser? He doesn't own the מעשר, maaser,
it's the לוי's. Levi's. Normally you have to be appointed as a
שליח, shaliach, okay? And so since when... and it doesn't sound like
we're making it, we're saying like implicitly the לוי Levi would want
the בעל הבית baal habayis like... it sounds like we're assuming like
the בעל הבית baal habayis is fundamentally entitled. It's my grain, I
separate off the מעשר, maaser, let me just go ahead and finish
the job, I'll take the תרומת מעשר trumas maaser from the מעשר,
maaser, like I have a right to do it because I'm the
one who separated it off. But since when is that true? Once
it's מעשר, maaser, it belongs to the לוי, Levi, okay, I mean,
you know, or the שבט לוי. shevet Levi. אִין, in, yes, אבא
אלעזר בן גמלא היא. Abba Elazar ben Gamla hi.
This is the position of אבא אלעזר בן גמלא. Abba Elazar ben
Gamla. דתניא, d'tanya, we learned in a ברייתא: Beraisa: אבא אלעזר בן
גמלא אומר, Abba Elazar ben Gamla omer, ונחשב לכם תרומתכם. v'nechshav lachem
trumaschem.
This is the פסוק pasuk by תרומת מעשר, trumas maaser, okay?
The פסוק pasuk is saying to the... to the... what's
the פסוק? pasuk? בני לוי ואל בני לוי ידבר תרומתכם מעשר מן
המעשר ונחשב לכם תרומתכם. Bnei Levi v'el bnei Levi yedaber trumaschem maaser
min hamaaser v'nechshav lachem trumaschem.
Right, it says you shall take a מעשר מן המעשר, maaser min
hamaaser, right, and so the לוי Levi will take a tenth of
the tenth, ונחשב לכם
תרומתכם. v'nechshav lachem trumaschem. Right, right, wait, hold on. Is תרומתכם trumaschem
going about the מעשר maaser or about the... hold on.
Let's see the פסוק. pasuk. 18:27? Okay, let's take a look.
Yeah, וחמליה מן היקב. v'chamleiha min hayekev. Okay, here.
ואל
הלויים תדבר
ואמרת
אליהם
כי תקחו מאת בני ישראל
את המעשר אשר נתתי לכם מאיתם בנחלתכם.
v'el haleviyim tedaber v'amarta aleihem ki tikchu mei'es bnei
yisrael es hamaaser
asher nasatti lachem mei'itam benachalaskhem. You are given
the מעשר, maaser, right? והרמותם ממנו תרומת ה׳ מעשר מן המעשר. v'harimosem
mimmennu trumas Hashem maaser min hamaaser.
You take a tenth of a tenth, that's your תרומת מעשר. trumas
maaser. ונחשב לכם תרומתכם כדגן מן הגורן וכמלאה מן היקב. v'nechshav lachem
trumaschem k'dagan min hagoren u'che'mleiah min hayekev.
And your תרומה teruma should be considered to you like the grain
from the threshing floor and the full from the vineyard. So what
does that mean? Your grain should be like you for תרומה. teruma.
So who's it talking to?
So basically, so רש״י Rashi says here, I'm just checking רש״י, Rashi,
but yeah, but since it uses the word תרומה, teruma, it means
your תרומת מעשר, trumas maaser, the way this is understood is your
תרומת מעשר trumas maaser that you'll be מרתק martek is like the
תרומה teruma that the ישראל Yisrael takes on his grain, okay? ונחשב
לכם
תרומתכם, v'nechshav lachem trumaschem,
okay, so your תרומת מעשר trumas maaser of the לויים Levi'im is
like the תרומה teruma that the ישראל Yisrael takes on his grain,
okay? בשתי תרומות הכתוב מדבר. bishtei trumos haksav medaber.
Now this is actually פשט peshat of the פסוקים. pesukim. The פסוקים
pesukim are talking about two תרומות. trumos. The תרומת מעשר trumas maaser
is like the normal תרומה, teruma, okay? תרומה בנובר, teruma b'nover, אחת
תרומה גדולה ואחת תרומת מעשר. achas teruma gedolah v'achas trumas maaser.
That's exactly what the פסוק pasuk is saying. So now here's the
הלכה halacha we learn from this. כשם שתרומה גדולה ניטלת באומד ובמחשבה.
keshem she'teruma gedolah nitteles b'omed u'b'machshava. The same way normal תרומה teruma
is taken by just, you know, estimating or we would say gestimating,
okay, and by thought. You can just think, you don't even have
to articulate, okay. How do we know those two are true? Well,
תרומה Terumah really
is even, הלכה Halacha is תרומה Terumah is even one grain exempts
the whole, kernel exempts the whole, threshing, the whole pile. So there
is actually no amount, you don't have to estimate if there is
no amount. So רש"י Rashi says okay but that's sort of the
point, the point is and halachically the amount is like two percent.
But because there's no fixed amount in the תורה, Torah, even if
you're doing the rabbinic two percent, you can just like guesstimate. תוספות
Tosafos actually says we actually encourage the estimating because we assume that
people are not going to want to
come self-short, sort of like cheat out
on the, it's sort of like how when by some the merchant
fills your thing and he pops it off, right exactly. So that's
why we sort of encourage the estimating because it means they'll sort
of round up and make sure they're not cutting short. But anyway,
but since תרומה Terumah doesn't have a fixed amount, you're never giving
a precise amount, so even when you give the rabbinic you're guesstimating
but there's no precise amount. So from there we learn that when
you give תרומת מעשר, Terumas Maaser, a tenth of a tenth, although
there is a precise amount, the tenth, you don't have to measure
it precisely. You can sort of guesstimate. Now you can't intentionally do
less or intentionally, you might be able to, תוספות Tosafos actually has
a whole long discussion in תוספות Tosafos that you might actually intentionally
be able to do more, okay, but anyway, but that's the idea.
It's a tenth but it could be a sort of like a
guesstimated tenth. Okay, that's באומד beomed and במחשבה bemachshavah is thought. How
do we know it can be done by thought? So רש"י Rashi
says that's the פסוק pasuk of ונחשב. venachshav. ונחשב Venachshav means like
במחשבה. bemachshavah. So you don't even have to verbalize and say הרי
זו תרומה. harei zo terumah. Not only do you not have to
physically separate the grain off from the pile like we learned in
an earlier משנה mishnah that you can sort of say the ten
percent is this, ten percent is that and then afterwards you figure
out which ten percent and you didn't separate it off but at
least you verbally said something. תרומה Terumah and תרומת מעשר Terumas Maaser
can be done purely by a thought act. Doesn't even have to
be verbalized. And we learn that from the word ונחשב. venachshav. Okay.
So אחת כשם שתרומה גדולה ניטלת באומד ובמחשבה כך תרומת מעשר ניטלת
באומד ובמחשבה. achas keshem sheterumah gedolah niteles beomed uvemachshavah kach terumas maaser
niteles beomed uvemachshavah.
That's all very interesting. What does this tell us about this question
about the בעל הבית baal habayis taking תרומת מעשר? Terumas Maaser? So
now we're going to say that. וכשם שיש רשות לבעל הבית לתרום
תרומה גדולה, ukeshem sheyesh reshus labaal habayis litrom terumah gedolah, the same
way the owner of the grain takes the תרומה גדולה, terumah gedolah,
so if we're comparing the two תרומות, terumos, כך יש רשות לבעל
הבית לתרום תרומת מעשר. kach yesh reshus labaal habayis litrom terumas maaser.
He's entitled to separate off the תרומת מעשר Terumas Maaser from the
מעשר. maaser. He separated off the מעשר, maaser, he's going to finish
the job and separate off the תרומת מעשר. Terumas Maaser. Yes, I
had an interesting question which isn't explored is who does he then
become entitled to decide which כהן kohen gets it? Right? So I
went ahead, I separated off the מעשר maaser and then I separated
off the תרומת מעשר. Terumas Maaser. I'm going to give you, the
לוי, Levi, the מעשר. maaser. Do I have to give you the
תרומת מעשר Terumas Maaser and you get to decide which כהן kohen
to give it to? Do I give another לוי Levi the תרומת
מעשר Terumas Maaser and that other לוי Levi gets to decide? Does
it have to go as a package? Or can I give it
to which I don't know the answer. Can I give it to
the כהן kohen I want to give it to? But anyway, but
at least I'm entitled to separate it off. Yes.
Okay, I have fields, we all have fields, there's one כהן kohen
in town. First I give my תרומה terumah and then I give
from the remainder of the field a מעשר maaser to the לוי.
Levi. Can I do it the other order?
No. I mean you can and it's קבוע. kavua. You're violating an
איסור. issur. I mean even an איסור דאורייתא issur deoraisa possibly. Okay,
fine.
I give a תרומה, terumah, everyone in town gives a תרומה terumah
to that one כהן kohen in town, he gets from everybody.
Yeah it could be that way. Yeah right sure.
Do I assume when the גמרא Gemara talks about כהנים kohanim that
all כהנים kohanim are חברים chaveirim or are there some No,
total כהן עם הארץ kohen am haaretz cases, right right
right, there's the same חששות chashashos about it.
Yeah and you shouldn't give to him.
I'm serious. Whatever. Okay. All right. All right, next משנה. mishnah. All
right, now that we started תרומת מעשר, Terumas Maaser, we're going to
have another one and you'll see it has to go it's all
basing itself on this paradigm of leaving the guy to deliver his
גט get and assuming he's still alive. Okay, that's sort of what
this is all continuing in that theme. המניח פירות להיות מפריש עליהן
תרומה ומעשרות. hameniach peiros lihyos mafrish aleihen terumah umaasros. Okay, now basically
what I'm going to do is I am going to set aside
in a particular room, whatever, a hundred bushels of whatever apples, okay,
or grain, whatever, but we'll say apples.
And now as I go through and I'm going to be
sort of collecting my apples and whatever in the field over the
course of the year, I'm going to be keeping a ledger and
every time I process another amount of apples, I'm going to say
oh great, so two more bushels of תרומה terumah from that room.
And when it finally gets to a hundred, then I know that
that whole room is all תרומה. terumah. You got the scenario? Okay.
So same type right? So I start setting that room as טבל,
tevel, okay, the stuff in that room. Okay, but the plan is
to eventually turn it all into תרומה. terumah. And as I start
getting other grain that's טבל tevel I keep on saying two more
apples in that room are תרומה, terumah, two more, two more until
I know that I've got the whole room תרומה. terumah.
Even though it's תרומה terumah in
like שלא מן המוקף, shelo min hamukaf, it's certainly שלא מן המוקף.
shelo min hamukaf. It also
some some some תרומה terumah and whatever more.
Well, that's true, but you know as long as I'm going to
keep on doing it and maybe I could sort of designate. I
understand.
Anyway, I don't know.
Anyway, that's the case. Okay? Or or the same with מעשרות. ma'asros.
Now תוספות Tosfos by the way says, if you look at תוספות,
Tosfos, he says המניח פירות hameniach peiros it says בארבע שבתות ימים
תורמין ארבעים דשייא שלא מן המקום. be'arba shabbatos yamim tormin arbayim de'shayei
shelo min hamakom. Like we just learned you're not supposed to do
it if they're not all together. How can I have my מעשרות
ma'asros and תרומה teruma out of the field and say that's going
to be the stuff I left in that room? They're not all
together. So תוספות Tosfos says okay well we allow that if it's
like ערב שבת. Erev Shabbos. So I'm concerned that sometimes it'll be
right before שבת Shabbos and I'll have to be מפריש mafrish תרומה
teruma whatever and I'm trying to get the stuff ready for שבת
Shabbos and I'll just add to that stuff in that room. Okay,
anyway that's the case. All right. Now המוציא מעות מפריש עליהן מעשר
שני. ha-mosi'os mafresh aleihem ma'aser sheni. Or I set aside 100 dollars
and as I'm in the process and I've done you know and
whatever I you know I have a couple different times that I
separate off מעשר. ma'aser. I get it's a מעשר שני ma'aser sheni
year and I want to transfer the value to money and I'm
going to bring the money to ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So I keep on
and I keep on you know adding it up until I have
separated until a full 100 dollars has been transferred and then I'll
like put aside more money and then begin the process again.
Like the case in the משנה. Mishnah. Right, exactly. So I do
that. מפריש עליהן בחזקת שהן קיימין. mafrish aleihem bechezkas sheheim kayamin. Okay,
so the שיעור shiur is the way it fits into the theme.
I do not have to be afraid. I can just lock it
up in that room and I don't have to be afraid that
something happened to the apples or something happened to the money. All
right. Now אם אבדו, im avdu, now let's say I go back
after I've been doing this for a few weeks or months and
I see that the apples aren't there anymore. Something happened to the
apples. Okay? Or they got robbed. I don't know. They got rotten,
something.
הרי זה חושש מעת לעת. harei zeh choshesh me'es le'es. I have
to be concerned about 24 hours. So what the פשט pshat of
that means, although we'll see it debated in the גמרא, Gemara, is
when do I have to think that that something happened? How how
long ago? And the הלכה halacha is well within the last 24
hours. Anything you did in the last 24 hours is void because
it might have been missing for the last 24 hours, but anything
before that you can assume it was okay, which seems like a
very arbitrary number, right? I mean if nobody's gone into that room,
nobody ever checks it, why all of a sudden should I assume
that if anything happened it must have happened recently as opposed to
three months ago?
Okay, so on the one hand you have a חזקה chazaka that
it was there. So what we're dealing with is and this is
exactly what the גמרא Gemara is going to look at in such
a great right conceptual place. You have what's called a חזקה דמעיקרא
chazaka d'meikara and a חזקה דהשתא. chazaka de'hashta. Okay, a חזקה דמעיקרא
chazaka d'meikara means what was the status quo. The idea is the
status quo was it was there. I can assume that the status
quo remained. Okay, but now I know that the current status is
different. And I should do I assume that the current status tells
me something about the previous status? So the earlier status was telling
me it was all the same. The current status is telling me
actually I should assume that things were in the past the way
they are right now, right? That's the חזקה דהשתא. chazaka de'hashta. The
same way things are now should indicate the way they were in
the past. So at what stage, which one wins out? And this
has an interesting פשרה pshara which is like, okay, the current status
can tell you something about the last 24 hours. But it seems
very, yeah, so תוספות Tosfos makes the נדה Nidda comparison. I don't
want to it's not exactly comparable, but yes there is a surface
comparison to the נדה Nidda case. Okay, anyway, so that's so that
is it's not clear why where that number comes from, but that's
what we say.
Let's read the תוספות Tosfos actually since Michael raised it. Okay. מעת
לעת בנדה דייק מאי טעמא שנתנו רבנן שיעור בנדה מעת לעת ותימא
דהכא מאי טעמא. me'es le'es benidda dayek mai ta'ama shenasnu rabbanan shiur
benidda me'es le'es veteima de'hacha mai ta'ama. So whatever the reason over
there is in נדה, Nidda, which isn't it's not relevant here. So
תוספות Tosfos wants we don't have to worry about the נדה Nidda
case. Why here do we say 24 hours? Like what is this
arbitrary number? ויש לומר דדווקא התם דייק v'yesh lomar dedavka hasam dayek
oh no, no, actually I'm sorry.
תוספות Tosfos actually his problem is why the גמרא Gemara there asks
and here doesn't even bother to ask.
Okay. So תוספות Tosfos actually doesn't explain why the number works here.
Okay. So forget that. Let's go back to the משנה. Mishnah. Hold
on, let me just finish the משנה. Mishnah. Okay. דברי רבי אליעזר.
divrei Rabbi Eliezer. That's what רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer said. Now this
is a interesting because it says דברי divrei it says ולדברי רבי
אליעזר u'l'divrei Rabbi Eliezer but it doesn't say if anybody else says
anything otherwise.
דברי רבי אליעזר או רבי אלעזר.
divrei
Rabbi Eliezer o Rabbi Elazar. So that's the side of the question
about that. I think רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, anyway רבי אלעזר, Rabbi
Elazar, I made that mistake before.
Anyway רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says,
בשלושה פרקים בודקין את היין. bishlosha perakim bodkin es hayayin. If you
do this with wine, wine can turn to vinegar. You can assume
the apples are still there or the money is still there, but
the wine you have to check periodically to make sure it's still
wine and not vinegar. Because you can't be מפריש mafrish vinegar on
wine. Okay, so בקידים של מוצאי חג be'kitom shemotei chag in the
eastern wind when there blows after after סוכות. Sukkos. ובהוצאת סמדר uvehotzas
smadar when the when the grapes start to like the very like
you know the smallest how do they translate סמדר smadar there? blossom.
What, the blossom? And ובשעת כניסת מים בבוסר ubishas knisas mayim baboser
and when the water starts going into the unripe grapes, when the
unripe grapes start filling. Okay, those are the times, you know, that
you have to check on what's going on with the wine. What's
your question Michael?
So if there is a so let's say the apples do rot,
right? Now you have to
say all right...
After I was מפריש mafrish up they're rotten?
Yeah, and I never gave them
to the כהן. Kohen.
So that becomes a problem about ממון שאין לו תובעין mammon she-ein
lo tovin because you were a שומר shomer for the whole שבט
shevet and no particular person in the שבט shevet can demand it
of you, you know, so that's like, it's an interesting question. Let's
say I steal it or whatever. I mean if you, it might
be, but let's take a case where actually you were מפריש mafrish
it for a particular כהן. Kohen. Right, then you would be liable
as a שומר. shomer. If you were פושע, poshea, then you'd have
to reimburse him. Okay, if you weren't פושע, poshea, it's a different
story. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this: מעת לעת. Me'es
l'es. So just even before we try to figure out what the
reason is, let's do like what does the word mean? Does it...
we've been assuming it means backwards the last twenty-four hours. So the
גמרא Gemara says: רבי יוחנן אמר מעת לעת שבדיקה. Rabbi Yochanan amar
me'es l'es she-bdika. Yeah, you take the time you checked and you
found that something was wrong and you're concerned that that state began
up to twenty-four hours ago. Anything in the last twenty-four hours is
bad. And we're concerned that that state took place, something happened, we
don't, right, within the last twenty-four hours. רבי אלעזר בן תנחום אומר
משום רבי אלעזר ברבי ינאי. Rabbi Elazar ben Tanchum omer mishum Rabbi
Elazar b'Rabbi Yanai. No, he says a much, a much more extreme
position. מעת לעת של הנחה. Me'es l'es shel hanacha. It means the
opposite. It means you have to assume that it was all bad,
it was always in this bad state and you can only assume
that the first twenty-four hours was good. So now you have to
be concerned that the last twenty-four hours was bad? You can only
assume that the first twenty-four hours was good now that you see
that it's bad right now. Okay? So the גמרא Gemara says, now
let's see which way fits in the language of the משנה. Mishna.
תנן, Tnan, the משנה Mishna says: חוששת. Chosheshas. I know. אם עבדו
הרי זו חושש מעת לעת. Im avdu harei zo choshesh me'es l'es.
If it's lost, you're concerned for twenty-four hours. בשלמא למאן דאמר מעת
לעת שבדיקה, Bishlama l'man d'amar me'es l'es she-bdika, your concern is for
the previous twenty-four hours. שפיר, Shapir, that fits the grammar, the language.
אלא למאן דאמר מעת לעת של הנחה, Ella l'man d'amar me'es l'es
shel hanacha, but if it's twenty-four hours from the time is good
from the time that it was set aside, so עד מעת לעת
Ad me'es l'es מיבעי ליה, mibaye lei, which is another way of
asking the חושש. choshesh. And חושש choshesh means what's the time I'm
concerned with bad. So that state... so if you want to say
you have to be concerned about all the way into the past
until you hit the first twenty-four hours, so it should be עד
מעת לעת. ad me'es l'es. Okay, so גמרא Gemara says: קשיא. Kashya.
You're right, that's difficult. Clearly the simple פשט pshat is you're only
חושש choshesh for the last twenty-four hours. Now: דברי רבי אליעזר. Divrei
Rabbi Eliezer. That's the opinion of רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. So the
גמרא Gemara fills in the blank. What do other people say? Excuse
me, דברי רבי אלעזר. Divrei Rabbi Elazar. I did that again. אמר
רבי אלעזר: Amar Rabbi Elazar: חולקין עליו חביריו על רבי אלעזר. Chalkin
alav chavayrav al Rabbi Elazar. דתנן, D'tnan, we talk in the משנה:
Mishna: מקווה שנמדד ונמצא חסר. Mikveh she-nimdad v'nimtza chaser. Okay, so here's
a perfect... of the classic example of when you have these competing
חזקות. chazakos. You had a מקווה mikveh that you measured out and
you knew it had the right amount of water and people have
been using it for months. And then you measure it again and
uh-oh, there's not enough water.
So when do we assume that the problem started? Right? It's been
sort of... probably it's been slowly leaking or whatever for a while
or people have been taking water out, you know, whatever. People come
out of the מקווה, mikveh, there's water on your body, so it's
been... a problem that's been going on for a while. When do
we assume that it became bad? Okay? So כל טהרות שנעשו על
גביו למפרע. Kol taharos she-nasu al gabav l'mifre'a. Anything that was used
for this, you know, vessels that were made pure or people, you
know, you know, that was used in the past for this. בין
ברשות היחיד בין ברשות הרבים, Bein b'reshus ha-yachid bein b'reshus ha-rabim, whether
the מקווה mikveh was in the private or the public domain. Even
though normally we say if something is in the public domain we
assume if there's a doubt about טומאה וטהרה tumah v'tahara we assume
it's okay. But here, wherever it occurred: טמאות. Tmei'os. We assume that
it was all bad. Now what's the logic for this? So the
basic logic is that this vessel here, which I took to the
מקווה, mikveh, right, and I was טובל tovel it, this vessel started
with a חזקה chazaka of being טמא. tamei. Its status quo was
טמא. tamei. Right, if we look at about it... the מקווה, mikveh,
the מקווה mikveh we have competing status quos, the past one and
the present one, and it's not clear where that's going to sort
of fall out. But let's ignore the מקווה mikveh for right now.
This had a חזקה chazaka of being טמא. tamei. And I was
טובל tovel it in a מקווה mikveh where now I'm finding out
that there was a doubt as to what the status of that
מקווה mikveh was in the past. So this doesn't change its חזקה
chazaka until I know for sure that that מקווה mikveh was okay.
And that's why this is assumed to be טמא. tamei. That's also
why it's true even in a רשות הרבים, reshus ha-rabim, because even
though we say ספק טומאה ברשות הרבים טהור, safek tumah b'reshus ha-rabim
tahor, that's when it's the opposite. This starts as טהור tahor and
I don't know if it touched something טמא. tamei. So then if
it's a רשות הרבים reshus ha-rabim you're fine. But this started as
טמא tamei and I don't know if it became טהור. tahor. So
then even in a רשות הרבים reshus ha-rabim we're going to say
assume that it has the status quo unless you know that a
good... that a good act of טבילה tvila was done to it.
And if that's true, it's also true by the grain. This no
longer is my... is a vessel, this now is are my apples.
And I was... they had a חזקה chazaka of being טבל. tevel.
And I was מפריש mafrish on those apples in the room. And
I was trying to change their status. But their status only changes
if those were good apples in that room. And I don't know
that that's the case. So these should retain their status quo of
being טבל. tevel.
Why do you call that this a חזקה chazaka of being טמא?
tamei? It was טמא! tamei! No, no.
חזקה Chazaka means... no, yes, right. But what the חזקה chazaka says
is you knew it was ודאי, vadai, you don't know if that
status changed. What happened after it went to the מקווה *mikvah*? So
the חזקה *chazakah* that it was טמא *tamei* before means that it
was, you assume it's still טמא *tamei* now even after it went
to the מקווה *mikvah* if the מקווה *mikvah* was in doubt. Alright?
So everything is טמא *tamei*. פשיטא דחלוקין *Pshita d'chalukin*. So of course
they argue. Like okay I know, of course. We have to realize,
you know, no to know that that case exists and that it's
relevant. But okay, now that we know it, it's clear that there
is that debate. מהו דתימא מאי למפרע מעת לעת קמשמע לן *ma
d'teima mai l'mafrea me'eis l'eis kamashma lan*. No, no, no, I might
have wanted to explain that מקווה *mikvah* case through the lens of
our משנה *mishna* and say when it says that all vessels used
in the past were no good, all the word past means is
the past 24 hours. Okay? So I might have tried to force
that משנה *mishna* into the position of רבי אלעזר *Rabbi Elazar*. And
we're saying no, רבי אלעזר *Rabbi Elazar* says you only have to
worry 24 hours, but we're saying if things have a חזקה *chazakah*
of being bad and then the thing that would make it good
has these competing... has this competing חזקה *chazakah*, has this cloud over
it, then those things remain in their previous state and are considered
to be no good. Okay?
But so even like a minute? Like in other words like I
know that you know one day is 3:00 PM.
Yeah, so that's sort of the other reading of the מעת לעת
*me'eis l'eis* of the first 24 hours. Like then I literally had
to be because from the minute I left that room, right? So
you know you can never have anything work perfectly, right? You have
to make some rules. Okay.
But how far back do you go in the מקווה *mikvah* case?
All the way back until the first... until a minute after... until
a minute after
you checked it. I measured it and it was 40 סאה *se'ah*
and then I went to the מקווה *mikvah*, I know that I'm
טהור *tahor*. But anything from that point on, right? If it was
never measured before until a year from then, everything in the last
year is טמא *tamei*.
That's what I meant. עד כדי כך *Ad k'dei kach*. The whole
year. Right, right. Alright, that's not a good...
I know. Okay, now you understand רבי אלעזר *Rabbi Elazar* that says,
you know, just the last 24 hours. Okay. So anyway let's take
a look. רבי *Rabbi*... okay. So רבי יהודה אומר בג' פרקים *Rabbi
Yehuda omer b'gimel prakim*. Now רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* says, you know,
you gotta check the wine three times because wine goes bad. תנא
בקידום של מוצאי חג של תקופה *Tana: bikidum shel motzei chag shel
tkufah*. The eastern wind after the סוכות *Sukkot* of the תקופה *tkufah*.
Okay now what תקופה *tkufah* mean? Basically רש"י
*Rashi* says it means it's a year... it's a normal year when
סוכות *Sukkot* falls out in the like in the fall after the
fall equinox. Okay but if somehow it's a little bit off and
סוכות *Sukkot* fell out before the fall equinox then this wouldn't... then
whatever. That's not the east wind we're talking about. תנא רבי יהודה
אומר בג' פרקים *Tana: Rabbi Yehuda omer b'gimel prakim*. Now since we're
talking about three times to check your wine, let's look at some
other places where there are three times during an agricultural cycle. I
guess. בג' פרקים מוכרין את התבואה *B'gimel prakim mocherin et hatvuah*. There
are three times when grain is normally sold. לפני הזרע *Lifnei hazera*
before the planting begins, ובשעת הזרע *ubesha'at hazera* during the time that
the planting begins. So I don't get it, לפני הזרע *lifnei hazera*
and ובשעת הזרע *ubesha'at hazera*, like isn't that all a continuous time?
Anyway so whatever. ובפרוס הפסח *Uvfros HaPesach* and 15 days before פסח
*Pesach*. ראש חודש ניסן *Rosh Chodesh Nissan*. ובשלשה פרקים מוכרין את היין
*Uvshlosha prakim mocherin et hayayin*. There are three times that the wine
is generally sold. בפרוס הפסח *Bifros HaPesach*, 15 days before פסח *Pesach*,
בפרוס שבועות *bifros Shavuot*, 15 days before שבועות *Shavuot*, ובפרוס החג *uvfros
hachag* and 15 days before סוכות *Sukkot*. Right, everybody needs it for
יום טוב *Yom Tov* I guess. Okay. והשמן מעצרת ואילך *Vashemen me'atzeret
va'eilach*.
I'm sorry, did I read that right? בפרוס היין ובפרוס פסח ובפרוס
חג *bifros hayayin uvfros Pesach uvfros hachag*. והשמן מעצרת ואילך *Vashemen me'atzeret
va'eilach*. And wine is sold from שבועות *Shavuot* onward. Okay oil, sorry,
oil sold from שבועות *Shavuot* onward. למאי הלכתא *L'mai hilchata*? What do
I care when is the time that these things are normally sold?
Okay other than to know like when is a good time to
go to the market. אמר רבא ואיתימא רב פפא לשותפין *Amar Rava
ve'itayma Rav Papa: l'shutafin*. Okay if you're in a partnership with somebody
and you're in a partnership with wine and he's not around to
consult with, okay, and the question is when to sell it on
the market to make the best profit, right? So normally you gotta
consult with your partner. But if it is the time that everybody
is selling it, okay, then you can go ahead and sell it
without, you know, and if he's not available to be consulted, you
can go ahead and sell it without consulting. Okay, so that's what
because because this is what everybody does. Everybody sells at this time.
Okay. מכאן ואילך מאי *Mikan va'eilach mai*? After these times, like after
these three times, like what is now the time to sell it?
Like you haven't sold all your wine. When is now considered the
time and my partner isn't around? When can I sell the rest
of it? So אמר רבא כל יומי פרקי הוא *amar Rava: kol
yomei pirkei hu*. Once these times are over, any day is the
right time. Right, sell it while you still have buyers.
Okay. So that's the discussion about that and other tastes of three
times. Now because the whole issue about the east wind was mentioned
as a time to check
your
wine, we're going to
talk about the
east wind a little bit. Okay. ויהי כזרח השמש *Vayehi kizroach hashemesh*
And was when the sun shone forth, ויהי כזרח השמש, and was
when the sun shone forth,
וימן אלהים רוח קדים חרישית, Vayaman Elokim ruach kadim charishit, God made
by Jonah, right, God made this eastern wind חרישית. charishit. So מאי
חרישית, mai charishit, what does that mean? What's that adjective mean? So
אמר רב יהודה, amar Rav Yehuda, בשעה שמנשבת, besha'at shemenashevet, when this
east wind blows, עושה תלמים תלמים, osa telamim telamim, it's like חורש,
choreish, it makes furrows, okay, בים. bayam. So it's sort of like
it makes these when you make a furrow in the
ground, right, so you get a mound of earth near it. So
this east wind so powerful when it blows, right, it makes these
furrows, it makes these waves in the ocean. אמרי ליה רבא, amlei
Rava, אי
הכי, i hachi, היינו דכתיב? hainu dechtiv? So what does it have
to do with the פסוק? pasuk? I mean that might be true
about the wind, but how's it fit the context? ותך השמש על
ראשו של יונה ויתעלף, vatach hashemesh al rosho shel Yonah vayitalaf, and
that the sun shone on the head of Jonah and he fainted.
So what does the fact that you have this east wind
that makes waves in the sea, how's that related? It sounds like
it's related to the heat, right? So your explanation didn't explain
air blowing on him.
Well, if it's hot air. Okay, anyway, that might be. So let's
see. Well, okay, but presumably you would want to use an adjective
that would emphasize the heat of it. It's one of those eastern
things
that have a חמסין, hamsin, you know, they have this
terrible hot wind.
Right. No, it's not denying that that's the phenomenon, it's just saying
the adjective should be expressing that part of it, right? The adjective
should not be saying a strong east wind. Who cares that it's
strong? It should be a dry east wind, a hot east wind,
right? So that's the point, just have the adjective be appropriate for
the
context. Okay, אלא אמר רבא, ela amar Rava, בשעה שמנשבת, besha'at shemenashevet,
משתקת כל הרוחות מפניה. mashateket kol haruchot mipaneha. So it's using the
word חרישית charishit like חרש. cheresh. It silences the other winds. The
other winds might
actually be cooling winds, and this silences the other winds and that
somehow expresses the idea that it creates this tremendous heat because none
of the other winds are
blowing. Okay. והיינו דכתיב, vehainu dechtiv, אשר בגדיך חמים בהשקט ארץ מדרום.
asher begadecha chamim behashket eretz midarom. Okay, so because your clothes are
hot by the silencing of the land from the south. אמר רב
תחליפא בר אבא אמר רב חסדא, amar Rav Tachlifa bar Abba amar
Rav Chisda, אימתי בגדיך חמים, eimatai begadecha chamim, when your clothes get
hot? בשעה שהשקיט ארץ מדרום, besha'at shehishkit eretz midarom, when the land
has been silenced from the cooling south wind. The east wind eliminates
those cooling winds and so your stuff gets, and we're going to
now find out that it's the south wind that is the most
of the cooling winds. So your clothes are hot when the land
is silenced from the south wind. Okay, שבשעה שמנשבת, shebesha'at shemenashevet, משתקת
כל הרוחות מ, I'm sorry, hold on. שבשעה שמנשבת, I mean I
think רש״י Rashi says מנשבת menashevet means the east wind. Hold on,
let me just
check. Right, so because when the east wind blows, it silences all
the other winds. Not, okay, משתקת כל הרוחות מפניה. mashateket kol haruchot
mipaneha. All right fine, so the east wind is the one that
comes with the heat and silences the other winds. The south wind
is the one that would have brought some cool air. רב הונא
ורב חסדא הוו יתבי. Rav Huna veRav Chisda hava yasvi. רב הונא
Rav Huna and רב חסדא Rav Chisda were sitting. חליף ואזיל גניבא
עלייהו. chalif ve'azil Gneiva alaiaihu. So גניבא Gneiva passed by them. Right
now if you might remember from earlier in the מסכת, masechet, גניבא
Gneiva was the one that was giving, who was it, עולא, Ulla,
I think, a hard time. He said
בני אדם קמים עלי בידי למסרם למלכות, bnei adam kamim alai bayadi
lemosram lemalchut, סרטית דכתב ליה, sirtayit dechasav lei, right, so okay, so
גניבא Gneiva was certainly causing problems just to some people. But anyway,
let's see what happens with him. And also what a name, גניבא.
Gneiva. Anyway, אמר חד לחבריה, amar chad lachavrei, so one said to
the other, ניקום מקמיה דבר אוריין הוא. neikum mikamei debar oryan hu.
We should stand up, he's a big תלמיד חכם. talmid chacham. אמר
ליה אידך, amar lei idach, we didn't know that about גניבא, Gneiva,
right? אמר ליה, amar lei, remember at the end of that story
earlier was that he was taken out in chains. Anyway, אמר ליה
אידך, amar lei idach, the other one said, מקמי פלגא ניקום? mikamei
palga neikum? We should stand up for somebody who causes מחלוקת, machloket,
for somebody who's so contentious, problematic? אדהכי, ad hachi, while they were
talking about whether they should get up for
him, אתא איהו לגבייהו, ata ihu legabaiaihu, he came in front of
them. אמר להו, amar lehu, and he said to them, במאי עסקיתו,
bemai asikitu, what are you talking about? Right, you know, just when
you're talking about somebody they walk into the room, what are you
talking?
Oh, well exactly. אמר להו, amar lehu, ברוחות. beruchot. Oh, we were
talking about the weather. Nothing, nothing, we were just talking about the
weather. Right, so now the wind. אמר להו, amar lehu, oh, okay,
okay, talking about רוחות? ruchot? I have some תורה Torah about that.
So אמר להו, amar lehu, so he said, הכי אמר רב חנן
בר רבא אמר רב, hachi amar Rav Chanan bar Rava amar Rav,
ארבע רוחות מנשבות בכל יום, arba ruchot menashvot bechol yom, four winds
blow every day. רוח צפונית מנשבת עם כולן, ruach tzonit menashevet im
kulam, and the northern wind blows with all of them. שאלמלא כן
אין העולם מתקיים אפילו שעה אחת, she'imalai kein ein ha'olam mitkaiyam afilu
sha'ah achat, if it wasn't for the northern wind, the northern wind,
רש״י Rashi says, is like perfect, not too hot and not too
cold. So if it wasn't for the northern wind, we would, everything
would be destroyed. Like we need that calming effect of the northern
wind. Okay, אין העולם מתקיים אפילו שעה אחת, ein ha'olam mitkaiyam afilu
sha'ah achat, ורוח דרומית קשה מכולן, veruach dromit kashah mikulam, the southern
wind, which we thought a minute ago was good, at least it
was cold, but okay, maybe it's a little bit too cold. Okay,
so that's the
most, that's the strongest. ואלמלא... ve'imalai... And if it was not this
Ben Netz, which apparently is some angel, if this some angel didn't
get in its way and like hold it back, מחריבת כל העולם
כולו מפניה, machrevet kol ha'olam kulo mipaneha, then it would destroy the
whole world with its I guess frost, chance to be another ice
age. שנאמר Shene'emar
המבינתך יאבר נץ יפרוש כנפיו לתימן. hamavinatcha ya'aver Netz yifros knafav l'teiman.
So from the understanding יאבר ya'aver from the word like אבר, eiver,
like the wing, the wings of נץ, Netz, of this angel will
spread out his wings to the south. So he spreads out his
wings and protects us from that overly cold south wind. רבה ורב
נחמן בר יצחק הוו יתבי. Rabba v'Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak hava yasvei.
So that was the end of that story. רבה ורב נחמן בר
יצחק Rabba v'Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak were sitting, הוו יתבי. hava yasvei.
הוה חליף ואזיל רב נחמן בר יעקב. Hava chalif v'azil Rav Nachman
bar Yaakov. Now רב נחמן בר יעקב Rav Nachman bar Yaakov was
passed by דייתיב בגוהרקא דדהבא. de-yasiv b'guharka d'dahava. He was sitting in
a golden not chariot, what do they call those things when you
carry people? Carriage?
Paladin? Palanquin? Palanquin? Okay, so he was being carried anyway, so in
this gold thing, this gold palanquin,
okay, דדהבא, d'dahava, ופריס עליה סרבלא דכרזי u'fris alei sarvala d'karzi and
he spread on him was this like was this like blue coat,
cloak. So what do they say, do they say blanket, what do
they say there? Cloak? Yeah, okay. So this like, okay fine,
blue or green, whatever it is, green probably. כרזי Karzi is green.
רבה אזל לגביה. Rabba azal lgabei. So Rabba went to greet him.
רב נחמן בר יצחק לא אזל לגביה. Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak lo
azal lgabei. Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak didn't go to greet him. אמר
דילמא מאיניש דבי ריש גלותא נינהו. Amar dilma m'einish d'bei reish galuta
ninhu. He said look, presumably if he's such a fancy in this
golden thing with this green cloak or whatever, he's probably associated with
the house of the Reish Galuta. I don't need to involve myself
with these politicians. רבה צריך להו. Rabba tzarich lehu. Rabba needs to
get close to them and be nice with them. אנא לא צריכנא
להו. Ana lo tzarichna lehu. I don't need them. Rav says he's
very wealthy, you know what, I don't need, you know, let the
politicians come to me, I don't need to go to the politicians.
Okay, anyway. כדחזא רב נחמן בר יעקב דהוה אזיל לגביה. Kid'chaza Rav
Nachman bar Yaakov d'hava azil lgabei. So when Rav Nachman bar Yaakov,
one minute, כדחזא רב נחמן בר יעקב דהוה אזיל לגביה, kid'chaza Rav
Nachman bar Yaakov d'hava azil lgabei, when okay right, wait, I'm just
trying to read who's the... רב נחמן בר יצחק Rav Nachman bar
Yitzchak who didn't go and now רב נחמן בר יעקב Rav Nachman
bar Yaakov went. Yeah. רב נחמן בר יצחק. Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak.
No,
רב נחמן בר יצחק Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak לא אזל. lo azal.
No, but who
was passing? No, רב נחמן בר יצחק, Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, רב
נחמן בר יעקב Rav Nachman bar Yaakov was the guy in the,
was
the guy in
the paladin. Right, right, right. רב נחמן בר יעקב Rav Nachman bar
Yaakov was the guy in the paladin. So כדחזא kid'chaza to the
point that רב נחמן בר יעקב Rav Nachman bar Yaakov was the
son-in-law of the ריש גלותא,
Reish Galuta, you've got Rashi says. Tosafot disagrees with that. Okay, anyway,
right, thank you. So okay, כדחזא kid'chaza now when he, רב נחמן
בר יצחק Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak who wasn't going, saw that רב
נחמן בר יעקב Rav Nachman bar Yaakov who's the guy in the
golden palanquin was coming to him, גליה לדרעיה, galya l'darei, he uncloaked,
he like, you know, uncovered his arm and אמר שדיא נשיב, amar
shadya nashiv, oh the wind is blowing. Like he like intentionally ignored
him. Like here he was, he was coming to him in this
fancy, you know, thing. So oh look at that, oh look what
time it is, oh look the wind is blowing. Okay anyway. אמר
רבה הכי אמר רב. Amar Rabba hachi amar Rav. אמר רבא הכי
אמר רב. Amar Rava hachi amar Rav. So this Rava says this,
Rav says אישא מפלת בו. isha maplet bo.
This type of a wind is one that, oh no, I'm sorry,
no, Tosafot says שדיא נשיב shadya nashiv means that the what do
you call it, that the actual palanquin was blowing? No, or the
שדא, sheda, how do they explain what translation do they give there?
The carriage is being blown by the wind.
Oh, the carriage is being blown by the wind. Okay, I'm sorry,
right. Okay, so שדיא shadya which is the שדא, sheda, the carriage
is being blown by the wind. Okay.
Okay fine. אמר רבא הכי אמר רב. Amar Rava hachi amar Rav.
Rava says this, Rav says אישא מפלת בו. isha maplet bo. This
type of a wind is so damaging that a woman can miscarry.
ושמואל אמר אפילו מרגליות שבים מרקיבות בו. V'Shmuel amar afilu margaliyot she'bayam
markivot bo. Even the pearls in the sea rot as a result
of it. ורבי יוחנן אמר אפילו שכבת זרע שבמעי אשה מסרחת בו.
V'Rabbi Yochanan amar afilu shichvat zera she'b'mei isha masrachet bo. Even semen
in a woman's body right will spoil and won't the child won't
be conceived. אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק. Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak.
Now רב נחמן בר יצחק Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak says, who's the
one who didn't go there, ושלשתן מקרא אחד דרשו. v'shloshtan mikra echad
darshu. And they all learned it from the same pasuk. כי הוא
בין אחים יפריא יבוא קדים רוח ה'. Ki hu bein achim yafria
yavo kadim ruach Hashem.
So now again this is the east wind where we started with.
That's the wind we were talking about. It will between brothers יפריא.
yafria. We'll see what that means in a minute. Coming from the
east, the wind of God. ממדבר יעלה ויבוש מקורו. Mimmidbar ya'aleh v'yeivosh
m'koro. It will come from the wilderness, from the desert and it
will dry up its source. Okay right, so ויבוש מקורו, v'yeivosh m'koro,
זה מקורה של אשה. zeh m'korah shel isha.
So dry up the source is the womb of the woman in
the case of the semen. So that's how one of them learned
that from this east wind. ויחרב מעיינו. V'yecharav mayano. The wellspring will
become dry. זה שכבת זרע שבמעי אשה. Zeh shichvat zera she'b'mei isha.
I'm sorry, the... Oh no, the מקורו *mekoro* was the miscarriage, right,
the baby that was already there. That would sort of, so that
would be the miscarriage. And you'll dry up the wellspring, זה שכבת
זרע שבמעי אשה *zeh shichvat zera shebemayei isha*. That is the semen.
הוא ישסה אוצר כלי חמדה *hu yishasseh otzar keli chemdah*, it will
sort of destroy or whatever, you know, the the the treasure house
of every of every precious vessel, זו מרים שביים *zu Miriam shebayyam*.
So that's where they get it from all of these effects of
the east wind. אמר רבא *amar Rava*, אדי סורא הוא דדייקי קראי
*adei Sura hu dedaykei kraei*. So this is like, you know, this
comes from the Sura people that they are the people of Sura,
they know how to read the פסוק *pasuk* like this, how to
read how to interpret the פסוק *pasuk* in the way you just
did. Okay, now the גמרא *Gemara* says, מאי כי בין אחים יפרי
*mai ki bein achim yafri*, how about the beginning of that פסוק
*pasuk*, what does that mean? Between brothers it will יפרי *yafri*, this
wind. אמר רבא *amar Rava*, אפילו שופסא בכופא דמרא רפיא *afilu shufsa
bekufa demara rafya*.
Even the the handle that's in the head of that of the
head of the axe, this wind will rot away. Now רש״י *Rashi*
says because if you've ever seen these pictures, right, of these of
this axe, right, sometimes like it sort of looks like, you know,
it's like this, right? You know what I mean? Like the handle,
like it sticks out from the top, like that, that wasn't a
great picture, but you get the idea. Anyway, so that's בין אחים
*bein achim* because there are two holes here, right, so it's going
between the two brothers as it were, you know, between that's the
בין אחים *bein achim*. Okay and יפרי *yafri* is רפיא *rafya*, it's
like a rearranging of the letters. So it'll cause it to like
to to weaken, you know, even that strong handle in the head
of the axe. רב יוסף אמר *Rav Yosef amar*, אפילו סכסא בדפנא
רפיא *afilu sachsa bedafna rafya*. Even a peg in a wall, I
don't know how to get to exactly בין אחים *bein achim*, maybe
because it's used to hang up a picture, so it combines two
things, right, it's the thing on the wall and the wall. Anyway,
also it will cause to weaken. רב אחא בר יעקב אמר *Rav
Acha bar Yaakov amar*, אפילו קניא בקופסא רפיא *afilu kanya bekufsa rafya*.
Even a like a like a wicker woven into a basket, it
will cause to it will cause to weaken. All right, so with
that we now know the effects of the eastern wind and הדרן
עלך כל הגט *hadran alach Kol HaGet*.